Guide to the Al cantío de un gallo Radio Program Audio Recordings
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Tape 189, 1995 December 8; 1 (Box 189)
  Side B: Melero and Franqui. 1. The deterioration of Castro's health and of Cuba; 2. Thoughts on the Polish presidential election of 1995 and Alexander Kwasniewski's rise to power. This recording contains two installments of the show. The first deals with Castro's health. Franqui gives us an anecdote from his time in the Cuban revolution when he and Castro climbed down a hill -- Franqui claims that he's never seen such an able, fit climber. The considerable deterioration of Castro's physical and mental health can only be considered a serendipitous factor in Cuba's struggle against him. As Castro's health has deteriorated, so has the state of Cuba -- and Cubans must get ready, Melero says, to make new laws and govern responsibly. In the second installment, Melero and Franqui talk about the recent Polish presidential elections, which brought Alexander Kwasniewski, a reformed communist, to power. Both speakers feel that this is a great example for Cuba, and that it acts as further proof that a transition from communism to democracy need not be bloody. Melero reads through an account of Kwasniewski's rise to power and an interview with the new Polish leader.
  Side A: Esta grabación contiene dos programas anteriores del show: el primero es una repetición de Tape 184, Side B y el segundo una repetición deTape 187, Side B.
  Side B: Melero y Franqui. 1. El deterioro de Castro y de Cuba; 2. Una discusión sobre las elecciones polacas de 1995. Esta grabación contiene dos programas del show. En el primero se discute la condición física y mental de Castro. Franqui nos cuenta de un momento durante la revolución en que él y Castro caminaban por las montañas -- Franqui dice que nunca ha visto un hombre tan fuerte y capaz de caminar. El deterioro físico y mental de Castro favorece la oposición por casualidad, un accidente que debe ser usado a su ventaja. Pero de la misma manera que la salud de Castro ha deteriorado, también ha deteriorado el estado de Cuba -- y los cubanos, dice Melero, se deben preparar para crear nuevas leyes y para transicionar a la democracia. En el segundo programa, Melero y Franqui discuten las elecciones polacas de 1995, en que el ex-comunista Alexander Kwasniewski se convirtió en el presidente de Polonia. Según los interlocutores, este acontecimiento es un buen modelo para Cuba y demuestra que la transición a la democracia no tiene que ser violenta. Melero lee un artículo sobre la ascendencia de Kwasniewski al poder y una entrevista hecha al líder polaco.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 190, 1995 December 11-14; 1 (Box 190)
  Side A: Melero, Franqui and Montijo. 1. San Lázaro and other Cuban saints; 2. A reflection on the state of human rights in Cuba; 3. Christmas: a lost tradition in Cuba. This recording contains three installments of the show. In the first, the speakers discuss San Lázaro (Babalú Ayé), a Cuban saint. They play "San Lázaro," a song by Celina y Reutilio, and read from a book about the saint by Lidia Cabrera. In the spirit of Human Rights Day, celebrated on December 10th, the speakers dedicate the second installment to a discussion on human rights. Melero and Franqui read through an article in the Miami Herald by Frank Garzon and a column by Pablo Alfonso, which includes two declarations -- one by Gustavo Arco and another by Lizardo Sánchez -- about the state of human rights in Cuba. In the third installment, Melero and Franqui, joined by Montijo, talk about Christmas. The holiday has disappeared in Cuba, given Castro's active attempts to suppress its importance. As a result, younger Cuban generations lack information about the tradition and its historical importance in Cuba. The speakers try to shed some light on the holiday, its history, and its biblical roots. They read relevant passages from the bible between brief musical interludes.
  Side B: Melero, Franqui and Montijo. Celebrating Christmas. This recording contains three installments of the show, all dealing with Christmas. Franqui begins the first show by explaining his decision to be an agnostic. In between musical interludes -- organ renditions of Bach's music -- Franqui reads from an Italian encyclopedia about Christ's life. In the second installment, the speakers discuss the symbolic importance of the Christmas tree and give advice to their listeners on how to make their own makeshift tree. In the third installment, the speakers read through Christmas-related selections of an 1881 chronicle by Cuban hero José Martí, written while he was in New York. The selections deal with the differences in the way Christmas is celebrated in the US and in the Spanish-speaking world. The installment ends with the speakers encouraging their Cuban listeners to get in touch with their spirituality and to rediscover the Christmas tradition.
  Side A: Melero, Franqui y Montijo. 1. San Lázaro y otros santos cubanos; 2. El estado de los derechos humanos en Cuba; 3. La Navidad: una tradición perdida. Esta grabación contiene tres programas del show. En el primero, los interlocutores hablan sobre San Lázaro (Babalú Ayé), el santo cubano. Tocan la canción "San Lázaro," grabada por Celina y Reutilio, y leen de un libro sobre el santo escrito por Lidia Cabrera. En el segundo programa, en honor del día de los derechos humanos, celebrado el día 10 de diciembre, los interlocutores discuten la importancia de los derechos humanos. Leen un artículo en el "Miami Herald" por Frank Garzon y una columna por Pablo Alfonso, en que aparecen dos declaraciones -- una por Gustavo Arco, y otra por Lizardo Sánchez -- sobre el estado de los derechos humanos en Cuba. En el tercer programa, Melero y Franqui hablan sobre la Navidad. Dado que Castro ha intentado suprimir la Navidad en Cuba, las nuevas generaciones cubanas son mal informadas sobre esta tradición. Los interlocutores hablan sobre la Navidad, su importancia histórica en Cuba, y sus raíces en la Biblia. Entre breves intermedios musicales, los interlocutores leen del evangelio de San Mateo.
  Side B: Franqui y Montijo. Celebrando la Navidad. Melero. Franqui comienza el primer programa hablando sobre su decisión de ser agnóstico. Entre breves intermedios musicales -- canciones de Bach tocadas en el órgano -- Franqui lee de una enciclopedia italiana sobre la vida de Cristo. En el segundo programa, los interlocutores discuten la importancia simbólica del árbol navideño y dan consejos a sus oyentes cubanos sobre cómo construir un árbol improvisado. En la tercera parte, los interlocutores leen fragmentos de una crónica de José Martí, escrito en 1881 cuando el héroe cubano estaba en Nueva York. Los fragmentos se tratan de las diferencias entre las maneras de celebrar la Navidad en los Estados Unidos y en el mundo hispana. El programa termina con la pedida de los interlocutores que sus oyentes cubanos a encuentren su espiritualidad y a redescubran la tradición navideña.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 191, 1995 December 23; 1 (Box 191)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui. A two-part discussion on Vaclav Havel. This recording contains two installments of the show, both of which deal with Vaclav Havel, the president of the Czech Republic who has recently visited the United Nations headquarters in New York. Melero and Franqui discuss his struggles as a political dissident and read a letter he wrote on the April 8, 1975, to Gustáv Husák, the then-General Secretary of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia. In the letter, Havel excoriates the fear-based communist system, accusing it of "existential coercion."
  Side B: Melero and Franqui. Cuba: Death or Resurrection? A discussion in two parts. The two installments that make up this recording both deal with an article written by Franqui called "Cuba: Death or Resurrection?" In it, Franqui considers Cuba's troubled history as a whole and attempts to diagnose its current state. Franqui and Melero discuss the toll that authoritarianism has taken, the effects of foreign intervention, and the longstanding contradiction between economic progress and politics on the island. The fall of the Soviet Union in 1989 has brought new hardships to the Cuban people but has also further discredited Castro's regime and prompted a more vocal discontent and opposition.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui. Una discusión sobre Vaclav Havel en dos partes. Esta grabación contiene dos programas del show, en los cuales los interlocutores hablan sobre Vaclav Havel, el presidente de la República Checa. Melero y Franqui discuten su legado como disidente político y leen una carta que escribió el 8 de abril de 1975, al entonces Segundo Secretario General del Partido Comunista Checo, Gustáv Husák. En la carta, Havel ataca el sistema comunista, afirmando que es basado en el miedo y que es nada más que la "coerción existencial."
  Side B: Melero y Franqui. "Cuba: ¿Muerte o Resurrección?" En los dos programas que constituyen esta grabación, Franqui y Melero leen y discuten un artículo escrito por Franqui titulado "Cuba: ¿Muerte o Resurrección?" en el cual Franqui considera la historia turbulenta de Cuba e intenta hacer un comentario sobre su estado actual. Franqui y Melero discuten los efectos del autoritarismo y la intervención extranjera, y la contradicción entre el desarrollo económico y la "mala" política. La caída de la Unión Soviética ha causado más sufrimiento para los cubanos, pero también ha logrado consolidar la oposición a Castro.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 192, 1995 December 27-28; 1 (Box 192)
  Side A: Melero, Franqui, Montijo and Rodolfo Silva. Cuba in 1995 and 1996. 1995 is coming to an end, and in two separate installments of the show the speakers take the opportunity to reflect on the year that has passed and the year ahead. Franqui feels that with each year the situation in Cuba gets progressively worse. Economic disparity is intensifying and foreign investments are lagging. As the economic crisis worsens, Cubans should join the opposition and work toward change. According to Montijo, all Cubans are responsible for the continued existence of the Castro regime, an ugly inheritance that new generations of Cubans must live with. In the second installment, Franqui argues that Castro is like Dr. Faustus for having sold himself to the Soviet Union. He also calls Fidel's possible replacement by his brother Raúl an ultimately empty move, as the two siblings represent the same thing. Montijo likens Castro's visible aging to that of Oscar Wilde's Dorian Gray.
  Side B: Melero, Franqui, Montijo and Rodolfo Silva. 1. Carnivals in Cuba; 2. Communism in Russia. This recording contains two installments of the show. Carnivals are to be celebrated again in Cuba, a development that the speakers choose to focus on in the first installment. Franqui gives the etymological and religious history of the carnival season. They play a carnival song, after which the speakers reminisce about the carnivals in Havana that they remember. In the second installment, the speakers discuss the recent legislative elections in Russia, which appear to have brought a slim majority for communists in the Duma. They consider the implications of this communist majority and mull over the state of the country. Franqui argues that the country is in the grips of two phenomena: the decomposition of its empire and the death of its former communist system. The speakers agree that while Russian communists pose more of a threat than, say, the ex-communists of Poland, it would be quite difficult for Russia to revert to the system it has left behind. Castro's celebration of a communist Duma is thus only symbolic.
  Side A: Melero, Franqui, Montijo y Rodolfo Silva. Cuba en 1995 y 1996. Se está concluyendo el año 1995, y los interlocutores, en dos programas del show, hablan sobre el año pasado y el año que viene. Franqui cree que con cada año, la situación en Cuba empeora. La desigualdad económica continúa y las inversiones extranjeras son mínimas. Dada la continuación de la crisis, los cubanos deben unirse a la oposición y trabajar para conseguir el cambio. Según Montijo, todos los cubanos son culpables por la herencia miserable del régimen castrista que sigue en existencia. En el segundo programa, Franqui dice que Castro es como el Doctor Fausto en el sentido de que ha vendido su alma a la Unión Soviética. También dice que la sustitución de Fidel por su hermano Raúl no tendría ninguna importancia actual, ya que los dos hermanos simbolizan la misma cosa. Montijo describe el deterioro de Castro como el envejecimiento de Dorian Gray, personaje creado por Oscar Wilde.
  Side B: Melero, Franqui, Montijo y Rodolfo Silva. 1. Carnavales en Cuba; 2. Comunismo en Rusia. Esta grabación contiene dos programas del show. En el primero, los interlocutores hablan sobre el carnaval que se celebra en La Habana. Franqui habla sobre la historia religiosa y etimológica del carnaval. Siguen con una canción del carnaval y cuentan sus recuerdos de experiencias relacionadas con esta tradición festiva en Cuba. En el segundo programa, los interlocutores hablan sobre las elecciones legislativas recientes en Rusia, las cuales han creado una mayoría comunista en la Duma. Consideran las consecuencias de los resultados de las elecciones y hablan sobre el estado del país. Franqui postula que Rusia está enfrentando dos fenómenos: la descomposición de un imperio y la muerte de un sistema. Los interlocutores están de acuerdo sobre un punto: aunque los comunistas rusos (que no son tan democráticos como los ex-comunistas de Polonia) presenten un peligro, la vuelta al comunismo total sería demasiado difícil e improbable. La celebración por parte de Castro de una Duma comunista es, por consiguiente, sin importancia.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 193, 1995 December 27-28; 1 (Box 193)
  Duplicate of Tape 192/Copia de Tape 192.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 194, 1996 January 5; 1 (Box 194)
  Side A: Raul Rivero's farewell to 1995; A letter from Cuban mothers to Vilma Espin. Melero and Franqui. 1. It's the night before Three Kings Day (Dia de Los Reyes), and Melero and Franqui take the opportunity to reflect on the rebirth of civil society in Cuba. They note that, despite the endemic dificulties in Cuba, the Cuban people have to some degree begun recuperating the freedom to think and speak. In particular, Cuban journalists have continued to release candid chronicles of life in Cuba to the world. Melero and Franqui read one such chronicle by Raúl Rivero, the director of Cuba Press, a group of Cuban journalists. Titled "My Farewell to the Year," Rivero's article is cynical in that it laments the death of the individual under communism but also optimistic in its hope that things will and can change. 2. In the second installment, Franqui begins by celebrating the important role that women have played in Cuba's history. They read a letter written by a group of Cuban mothers to Vilma Espín, Raúl Castro's wife and president of the Federation of Cuban Women, denouncing the sizeable population of women in Cuba's prisons. The letter lists specific women that have been arrested for dissenting from the Cuban regime, and argues for their immediate release.
  Side B: [Duplicate of Tape 192, Side A.]
  Side A: La despedida de año de Raúl Rivero; Una carta de las madres cubanas a Vilma Espín. Melero y Franquí. 1. Es la Noche de los Reyes en Puerto Rico, y en el primer programa del show Melero y Franquí toman la oportunidad para reflejar sobre el renacimiento de una parte de la sociedad civil en Cuba. Notan que a pesar de las dificultades endémicas de Cuba, la gente cubana está lentamente recuperando la libertad de pensar y hablar. La comunidad periodística de Cuba sigue publicando crónicas de la vida en Cuba, dando al mundo un retrato de la Cuba actual. Melero y Franquí leen una de estas crónicas, escrito por Raúl Rivero, el director del grupo de periodistas Cuba Press. Titulado "Mi despedida de año," la crónica es simultáneamente escéptica, ya que lamenta la muerte del individuo a causa del comunismo, y optimista por la idea de que el cambio sí puede ser realizado. 2. Franquí comienza el segundo programa celebrando el papel importante que la mujer cubana ha tenido en la historia de Cuba. Los interlocutores leen una carta escrita por algunas madres cubanas a Vilma Espín, la esposa de Raúl Castro y presidente de la Federación de Mujeres Cubanas, en que denuncian el encarcelamiento de muchas mujeres cubanas. La carta incluye nombres de mujeres encarceladas por haber disidido de la postura del estado y también demanda la liberación inmediata de las mismas.
  Side B: [Copia de Tape192, Side A.]
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 195, 1996 January 5; 1 (Box 195)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui. 1. The showdown over Medicare/Medicaid; 2. On a French study of political prisoners in Cuba. This recording contains two installments of the show. In the first, Melero and Franqui discuss the recent showdown between President Clinton and the Republican party in the Republican-dominated US Congress over the issue of Medicare/Medicaid and Social Security. The paralysis that has resulted from the debate has even started to affect Cuba, with transmissions from Radio Martí and other 24-hour stations on halt. Franqui reads an article by the New York Times about the crisis, and he notes that this debate is not just occuring in the US but around the world. In post-Communist countries, for example, where the fall of totalitarian states has left large gaps in government programs, healthcare has been an important issue in recent elections. In the second installment, Melero and Franqui read through and discuss an article about a recent study commissioned by the French government on the state of Cuba's political prisoners. Conducted over the course of a week in Havana, the study admonishes Castro for continuing to take political prisoners and for placing them in such squalid conditions and calls for the immediate release of all political prisoners. Franqui talks about corruption in Mexico and how Cuba has acted as a haven for the wanted Gortari family. This is merely a symptom of the widespread corruption in Cuba, which has rendered many industries inefficient.
  Side B: Melero, Franqui and Montijo. 1. A letter from a prostitute: a discussion on Cuba's sex tourism; 2. "A Letter of Hope," by Cuban priest Conrado Rodríguez. This recording contains two installments of the show. In the first, Montijo reads a letter written by an anonymous prostitute to a statue of the Virgin Mary in El Cobre, Cuba. The young woman wishes to quit her profession and become a doctor; she asks for continued health and help in making the transition. To Franqui, the young woman reminds him of Mary Magdalen. He firmly believes that Castro and his regime are to blame for the sex tourism industry in Cuba, which continues to grow. Melero agrees, arguing that the prostitutes themselves are victims -- only Castro can be blamed. In the second installment, the speakers read through a letter by Conrado Rodríguez, a Cuban priest. In the letter, titled "A Letter of Hope," the priest argues against materialism and moral corruption and calls for a more just, prosperous, and morally sound country.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui. 1. La lucha política sobre Medicare/Medicad; 2. Investigación sobre el estado de los presos políticos en Cuba. Esta grabación contiene dos programas del show. En el primero, Melero y Franqui discuten la lucha política en el Congreso de los Estados Unidos entre el presidente Clinton y el Partido Republicano sobre el asunto de Medicare/Medicad y la Seguridad Social. La parálisis en el gobierno estadounidense ha empezado a tener efectos en Cuba: los programas de radio como los de Radio Martí han cesado. Franqui lee un artículo del New York Times sobre el asunto. Según Franqui, este debate sobre la crisis sanitaria está ocurriendo en todas partes del mundo. En los países ex-comunistas, con la caída del estado totalitario y el fin de muchos programas del gobierno, la asistencia sanitaria ha sido un tema importante en elecciones recientes. En el segundo programa, Melero y Franqui leen y discuten un artículo sobre una investigación comisionada por el gobierno francés sobre el estado de los presos políticos en Cuba. Los investigadores pasaron una semana en La Habana entrevistando a prisioneros escogidos por la Amnistía Internacional. En el informe final, los investigadores reprenden a Castro por continuar tomando prisioneros políticos y por las condiciones en que están encarcelados, e imploran que los prisioneros sean liberados inmediatamente. Franqui habla sobre la corrupción en México y el hecho de que Cuba haya sido un refugio para los miembros de la familia Gortari. Este es un síntoma de la corrupción en Cuba, que ha destruido la integridad de la economía cubana.
  Side B: Melero, Franqui y Montijo. 1. Carta de una prostituta: una discusión sobre el turismo sexual en Cuba; 2. "Carta de la esperanza" del Padre Conrado Rodríguez. Esta grabación contiene dos programas del show. En el primero, Montijo lee una carta escrita por una prostituta joven a la Virgen de la Caridad, cuya estatua está situada en El Cobre, Cuba. La joven desea salir de su profesión y hacerse doctora, y pide a la Virgen que le ayude con esta transición. Franqui dice que la mujer le hace pensar en la Biblia, en particular en la figura de María Magdalena. Según Franqui, Castro y su régimen son culpables por el turismo sexual en Cuba. Melero dice que las mujeres condenadas a la prostitución no tienen la culpa -- sólo el victimario, Fidel Castro, es culpable. En el segundo programa, los interlocutores leen una carta escrita por el Padre Conrado Rodríguez. En la carta, titulada "Carta de la esperanza," el sacerdote lamenta la corrupción moral y el materialismo de Cuba y describe su visión de una Cuba próspera, justa, y dirigida por la moralidad.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 196, 1996 January 9; 1 (Box 196)
  Side A: Cuba: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. A Refuge for Criminals. The speakers argue that Cuba is becoming a refuge for international criminals. Salinas de Gortari, the ex-president of Mexico, is accused of gaining millions of dollars in drug money and now lives in Cuba. Diego Maradona, a drug addict and a distributor of cocaine, has plans to retire to Cuba. In the 1970s, Fidel Castro welcomed Ramón Mercader, the murderer of Leon Trotsky, into Cuba. Castro befriends criminals because "birds of a feather flock together." The international world looks down on corrupt governments involved in drug trafficking, such as Colombia, Mexico, and now Cuba.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. A Socialstist Brothel. Franqui, Carlos. A group of independent Cuban journalists published an article about the "socialist brothel." Many Cuban women cannot afford to buy food for their families, and are driven to sell their bodies. This has attracted many sexual tourists from Spain. The speakers argue that if the "socialist brothel" is the price for Cuba's supposed economic development, it is better to allow independent organizations to function freely. Cuba is becoming a center for sexual tourism, corruption, and drug trafficking. Melero highlights Castro's hypocrisy, likening his acceptance of Gortari into Cuba to Trujillo's aid and acceptance of Batista.